And so I think you have to imagine what
would happen once trust is gained and
change is accepted if it is correct and
that is the area native destination.
Then you have to think about what's your
journey to it because if you just start
there nobody's going to use the product
and the product is not yet worthy of the
trust. A big investment in curation of
trying to map out a good number not at
all all AI dev tools out there. We've
mapped out I think about 170 tools at
creation. We already have a bunch of
contributions. What does it mean when
you start to talk about actually moving
from a code ccentric way of developing
to a specentric? This is probably the
most important part of what kind of
Tesla is going after in my
opinion. You're listening to the AI
native dev brought to you by Tesla.
[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI native dev. Today we really
wanted to share with you a very recent
meetup recording from London Gen AI
community and the community is run by
our friends at Google Ventures GV and
Tom Holm had a fireside chat with Guy
Pagani where they covered a number of
topics. Guy compares the AI native dev
movement to cloud native and talks about
some of the similarities uh there that
lie within and also talks a little bit
about the landscape of AI native dev
tools and the recent landscape.ai
nativedev.io comparison and
categorization that was released not so
long ago. guy also talks a little bit
about what specentric means and how
developers will be building in a
specentric way and also talks about
obviously the LLM magic is wonderful but
how do we harness that how do we
actually benefit from the way in which
LLMs can generate code there's a lot to
talk about and I'll hand over straight
to both Tom and Guy enjoy the session
we thought we'd kick off and just give
you a quick run through of the evening
So, initially, uh, Guy, who we've known
for just under a decade since the
sneaks, we'll have a conversation about
Guy and Team's new company, Tessle. Many
of you will have heard about it, but
very few know what they're doing yet, so
it's going to be exciting. But maybe to
kick off, we can jump straight into
Tessle. We're at an amazing time where
every day generative AI is changing and
the way that we're all working is
changing. We're going to focus the
conversation mainly in software
development this initial conversation
but you've talked about AI native
software development as a kind of new
paradigm. What does that mean? I guess
first of all thanks for hosting me over
here and thanks everybody for for
coming. Hopefully there's a few
interesting tidbits. I think AI is a
transformative a disruptive technology
and I think when we use it today when we
look at the places where we embrace it
the most often times it's actually in a
sustaining way. It's in a place in which
we embrace it into our existing
workflows. And that makes sense, right?
We don't want to change much. And so
we're taking kind of the way we work
today and we automate parts of it. And
that's also true in software
development. We've basically created
many different ways to like different
UXs to create code. And it's not to
belittle it like those are very valuable
and they automate it. But I guess our
belief, my belief is that the true
opportunity in any transformative
technology and very much in AI is to
rethink the workflows themselves. And
that that takes a while. It's not as
easy because you need to change, you
need to modify something. We're going to
have Cynthsia here later. That's a great
example, right? You can use AI to
sharpen images in video cameras that you
take and that is very valuable but the
true potential comes from some sort of
textto video experience that really like
100x a thousandx that totally changes
the game in terms of what you can do and
we've seen that on the development side
with cloud. there's it's nice to move to
something that is elastic or to use some
sort of cloud storage of it but the true
benefit from cloudnative development as
we call it today comes from practices
from changes that really embrace it the
sort of the plethora of services and so
I guess when we talk about a native
development is a little bit of a mandate
to dare consider different paths like
different workflows and I think we have
thesis we'll talk about that a little
bit later about how that would look like
but I think it's also a a community
exercise a movement of trying different
things that the challenge the way we
work, the way the workflow is to find
things that are AI native. They're
designed to say if you thought from
first principles, how should I do this
given the sort of powerful new beasts
that are these LLMs? This is how I would
build it. And we've sometimes talked
about the idea that you can go straight
to the end goal, the level five
autonomy, or you can build up over time.
You're imagining the end state now and
then thinking through how can we get
there. Yeah. And I think to an extent
there's no end state like of course
these things continue to evolve but yeah
it's I talk we're not going to belabor
this too much but I talk about both the
level of trust how much you trusted to
get it right being a factor and the
level of change how much do I need to
change how I work and so I guess in
general I think startups should anchor
in the future you should think about
what would be more needed in five years
time and therefore try to build towards
it and so I think you have to imagine
what would happen once trust is gained
and change is accepted if it is correct
and that is the area native destination
Then you have to think about what's your
journey to it because if you just start
there, you probably nobody's going to
use the product and the product is not
yet worthy of the trust. And there's so
many tools out there at the moment.
We've talked a lot about how it's hard
to make sense of the change and the kind
of the ecosystem. Help us understand how
you think about those tools. How are you
categorizing them? Yeah. So, as luck
would have it, we've actually done a
very thorough project to to map
precisely that. And today we launched
the the A native dev tool landscape.
It's been a monthful. We need to shorten
that out. It is a big investment in
curation of trying to map out a good
number, not at all, all AI dev tools out
there. We've mapped out I think about
170 tools at creation. We already have a
bunch of contributions proposed just in
the few hours that it's been out that
try to bucket all the different AI
developer tools. We charted them. We try
to think of many ways in which we can
bucket them together to say what are
these tools that help us integrate AI
into a software development across its
different stages. We put it mostly
across the development life cycle from
your kind of product design
requirements, prototyping phase into
your coding into your quality assurance
and devops and and eventually we also
included just a section that felt
inevitable around a little bit about AI
infrastructure that you might run on and
we gave a little bit of information
about each of those and so we launched
that today. We we really feel like today
you're lost if you're a developer and
you want to use a tool you probably know
of some five or six different things and
by the way they all sound the same. We
can come back to that a bit. There's no
real kind of reasonable way I'm not even
going to say easy to find out what is
out there. They change like so fast. So
finding what is there like even just
getting tonomy for it. So this is a part
of a broader initiative we have in the
AI native dev to try and help us wrangle
the sort of chaotic ecosystem capture
these tools. We take submissions from
from the community around different
changes, different additions that we
need to do. We ourselves will invest and
curate them. We'll add more information,
case studies, demos, examples of those
terminology to try and just pull it
together to try and move us towards
indeed the understanding of what is AI
native development, what are the
different lenses, different opinions on
it and wrangle it and we'll also
integrate over time news and others to
again just stay on top of this super
important but so messy, so fast
changing, so chaotic domain. I think
guy's point is important. This is very
much sort of UGC. We're hoping that
everyone will submit to this and it'll
start to be a living kind of repository.
In fact, you're using GitHub to run it
and indeed. So, we think in general AI
native development is a movement. It's
not something that is one product. We're
trying to help scaffold that, help
facilitate it. And so, we're doing that
across many things. We run a virtual
conference on it. We host kind of people
on the podcast to share their learnings.
And this is part of it. So, it's open
source. It is it has a repo where you
can post contributions on it. Someone
does need to curate it. Someone needs to
say, "Yeah, this is just marketing."
versus we try to make sure that we
optimize it for the user, the primary
user, which is a developer wanting to
understand how do I use this to develop
software with AI. Got it. And so if you
step back, there's 170 plus tools on
there. It's been updated since we took
the screen grab. What are some of your
observations when you look across the
ecosystem? It's messy. I'd say maybe a
bit also on challenges we've had
building it. So one the scope of tools
is very illdefined. I think when we know
what an IDE is, we know what a build
system is, we know what whatever a git
repository or a git platform is in in
this domain both everybody wants to say
they are everything and none of them
actually do it to completion. And so
there's a lot of features that come from
different disparit parts of the
development process and it's I think
very much still in flux about what is a
cohesive value proposition. The places
where I think we know a little bit is
like coding assistance. I think we know
what that is. But even those products
are now growing to say, hold on, I also
have a chat and I'm going to build a
bunch of things on it. Okay, so are you
now an agentic system? I don't think
we've fully solved it here. We tried it.
We're going to tag a bunch of things,
but I think that is very evident that
the scope of tools is hard and I think
that's going to be hard for people when
they adopt it because they don't know
precisely where it sits. I think the
second thing we've observed is that
there's actually very little loyalty. So
this is not yet fully in the landscape
but what we see is that two years ago
you'd ask people which ID you use and
you'd have absolutely one year ago sort
of get one answer right whatever that
answer is you'd get one answer today you
talk to people that embrace these tools
as we talk to them people move around
they'd use wind surf here and cursor
there they'd use multiple different
tools trying out to to create the
requests they definitely try out
different observability or sort of a
some s part of it is because neither of
these tools really deliver on the
promise fully and so you see a lot of
tools that are like making the big
promise delivering a piece of it. But I
think that's another aspect which is
very like low loyalty between them and
that very much relates to low
differentiation. What are you see a lot
of these tools you try to analyze them
try to kind of map them out and they
feel very sy again not to say that
they're not valuable they're very
valuable but differentiation is rare in
any of these tools. So I think those are
the primaries. In addition to that I'd
say definitely heavy emphasis on
co-pilots and assistants. you actually
see very few autonomous claims. The ones
that are autonomous are almost entirely
behind waiting list controlled access
type level and again probably evident
that a lot of the tools are just not
fully mature and and it's hard like it's
easier to create a promise and to create
a demo but the gap the chasm between
that and actually a reliably working
product let alone an autonomous product
is there. So you see many different
co-pilots. I think those are the
primaries. I think there are some
emerging UX patterns as you dig into the
products themselves. We're going to try
and tag them. The obvious one being
chat. There's newer ones around pointing
and commenting threads on it. Visual is
getting more and more proactive on it.
Especially on the design side. The
ability to interpret an image has
boosted. And yet there's a a burgeoning
open source ecosystem over here as well
which is which is nice in practically
every category. We had some good open
and then I guess some of the other
trends we've seen just looking at this
one is natural language as an interface.
something that we're seeing partly
because LLMs are good enough at
transcription today. If you look at just
the code tool, one axis you and I have
talked about before is you got
traditional development on one end.
You've got completely agentic dev at the
other. You've got something around
citizen developers next to that lovable
bolt. One of our portfolio companies
we're excited about also Versel maybe.
Then cursor and wind surf like if you
look at cursor and wind surf as a sort
of example where we meet people that are
switching and literally say it's a
two-minute switch because VS code the UX
is the same. The sort of foundational
model it plugs into is the same. There's
no moat here like how might they
differentiate? How do you think about
that? So I absolutely agree they're all
very much the same and you move them and
the patterns are the same. The natural
language or the VS code fork or whatever
those are. I think I think today a lot
of them try to differentiate by a claim
that they are better in the way that
they deliver the value like how well
does it complete things or how well does
it build it's very hard to back those
claims it's like a very vibe testing
vibe check type work and so I think
today it's hard to to me what I see too
little of is attempts to really think
about that sort of workflow change to
destination there's so much gold in kind
of them hills of going of after today of
selling products that would work into
the existing workflow and automate on it
that just everybody is chasing the exact
same thing. I think the right way for
them to differentiate in the long run is
to think more long run. Now granted
maybe some of them have strategies that
are not there but when you even listen
to a lot of these founders in podcasts
or sort of others when they describe it
many of them talk about hey we like
we're leaning it we're delivering the
value today and we're aiming to be fast
to be ahead. you should be fast, you
should try to be ahead, but but I think
that's not a destination. So, I think
what will happen is we'll see a lot of
them like the smaller ones are probably
just getting lost in the shuffle, right?
You definitely see cases where there's a
hundred different companies doing the
same thing. And so, for those, it's just
hard to even break out of the crowd. And
then for the ones that become big, I
know Bolt, Lovable, Base 44 now came out
of somewhere, Versel. So all of those
tools that are have enough some critical
mass to to emerge on it. I do think that
they hit a bit of a wall like they hit a
bit of okay now you've built with these
products you you got to some sort of
level of functionality and as long as
you don't rethink the workflow you're
limited in the amount of value that you
Yeah makes sense. I think one of the
things we all have recency bias in
everything we do and I think one of the
counter
examples would be everyone saw open AI
believed that the tech would get
disrupted relatively quickly. You could
argue it was, but it quickly became a
consumer business because of basically
PLG. It it became ubiquitous and it's
still the sort of standout business. So
I think if I had to make an argument for
this sort of quick ramp like these
businesses that are getting to 100
million revenue run rate in less than
six months. I think their argument would
be it may be sticky. we need to be the
brand and get to scale and then the
dream is we might get to enough data
that we can maybe fine-tune our own
model or we can move the workflow
forward that you describe. Yeah. Yeah.
And I think it's not um unfounded that
claim and you need to get when you look
at I know cursor's level of adoption
clearly they have a large volume of
users now and they probably have some
data and they can use it. I will say
that building better models has not
proven to be a very deep moat and so if
your workflow this is just an opinion
here but if your workflow is the same if
you are easily swapped because even
people that swear by cursor still they
try winds surf and they're fun of it and
they're not that loyal and so clearly
there's something there that's missing
same for the models I think on the
consumer side actually people are even
more loyal in chat and such just because
they build their habits and they around
it and I think the dream is they start
to embed memory and that is remote. It's
understand me. It's a mode to the extent
we're not there yet. Yeah. Yeah. Just
kind of a challenge of the bit. It's a
mode to the extent that it's not
exportable and there's a certain overlap
between the the type of visibility you
want for something to has to have human
oversight and making that be something
that is your it's actually I' not I'd
never thought about that before, but we
I've always thought chat is completely
interchangeable. Zero friction to move
because it's just a text box, natural
language, but the foundation models get
commoditized by distillation. The
interesting thing is actually your
personalized version of a foundation
model with memory can probably get
distilled as well. There'll be some sort
of way to access it. So maybe even the
memory and the customization isn't as
defensible. How about the gaps in this
landscape? What are the big as you
looked at it? What are the big areas
you're surprised no one's building?
There's loads of builders here in the
audience. What would you be going after
having looked at this landscape if you
were starting today? I think yeah I
don't think there's any stone that is
entirely unturned I think it's like hey
there's only 20 startups in this space
there's still room there of it yeah so
again one co-pilot to to autonomous like
very lacking in autonomous development
or autonomous activity and I think
there's opportunity to find slices that
you can perform that are substantial
that are true that you dig into and that
you can provide those autonomously I
think those are very valuable we're
seeing that a little bit I think there's
definitely more adoption in the so I
would almost buck it into these sort of
four buckets that we put right in the
product side I think there is less
evolution or less maturity around the
design side around the requirement side
there are far fewer tools in that space
I think maybe there's adopted in a
little bit less volumes of it the code
side is definitely the most busy many
users but many tools like in a large
large degree the QA side the quality
assurance you see a lot of enterprise
focus and I think there's there's kind
of this hope that this reinvigorates
testing. I think focusing on specific
stacks, focusing on specific niches
there is working well and I think there
are still wide areas over there and the
technology seems to be feasible today.
And then lastly in the sort of the
DevOps SR space I think people are
they're just very afraid to have
autonomy there. So there are a few
companies that are building autonomous
agents that are in the calendar sale
plane there traversal but typically
there's just a lot of sifting through
data type opportunity. And again I think
niching into a specific solution a
specific domain in which you can provide
autonomy feels like a real opportunity.
I think yeah one of the just building
off that one of the areas we've observed
is we ask ourselves where where is
generative AR LLM's kind of reliable
enough today and we've not really found
any fully agentic reliable enough tools
where they're most reliable is where the
training has been cleanest. So that's
obviously coding legals are phenomenal
for this. That's a space we've invested
in a lot for that reason. Customer
service is one we're looking at all the
time now. Whether it be text or voice,
it's good enough. So, people are
starting to ask this question, what
about reliability? Because for scale,
you have to get there. And it's why
coding may actually be representative of
what you're going to see happen to other
industries because it was one of the
most reliable, fastest. Yeah. And and
and I would say though in in co-pilot
mode because like coding autonomous
coding right now is is still failing by
the dros even in the sort of the top
companies. So you you shared a fun video
before this which is and maybe we're
going to jump in and show in a second
but just on that around reliability and
this idea that code is there's just an
explosion of code probably bad code.
What does it mean when you start to talk
about actually moving from a code
centric way of developing to a spec
centric? This is probably the most
important part of what kind of Tesla is
going after in my opinion. What is
specentric code? When we think about
things from first principles and say
what is software development going to
look like and you have to make some bets
and think about where it's headed. We
realized that one of the one of the
constraints that we have today is that
we need this translation layer between
code and between sort of humans and
machines and that is satisfied with
code. And today like software
development is really revolved around
that code. And so you get some
requirements, you get some sort of tasks
you need to build, you write some code
while you write the code you make a
hundred decisions that never make it out
of the code. Over time you get more
requirements, more changes. The code
evolves, the requirements get thrown by
the wayside, right? And it's like
walking into this room and look at the
curtains and the screens and the sort of
the choice of desks here and the
elevation and lamp and you don't know
which of these are like compliance
requests of accessibility versus things
that have been designed in and which
ones were budget decisions and which
ones are corporate colors. You just need
to guess that right and similar to the
code you come along you look at what's
there and you say what am I allowed to
change I don't know look around apply
common sense they lost a lot of data and
over time as systems grow they become
very fragile in that fashion and and I
think we have an opportunity to change
that around so with LLMs we have the
ability to go and think about something
at a on one hand at a higher abstraction
level and so we can talk about the
systems that we want in in in natural
language in visuals in all of these
great tools that alums give us today to
descri describe what we want and
secondly is we can choose the line of
adaptability that we want to give to be
able to tap into the magic of LLM
decision-m and so we can say hey it's
really important for us that there's a
ramp over here using physical terms here
right and that the purple color because
that is the design decision on it but
we're fine delegating to the LM the
placement of the TVs around and by by
making that decision over time when TVs
change and all of that LM are adaptable
so we no longer need to maintain our
decisions as much the LLMs can make that
decision. I think today you can go to a
bolt or or any of those tools on it
which are powerful still today but
generally you chat away and you really
try to delegate like there's a lot of
there's a range in which you delegate a
lot of decisions on it and you have no
way really to define what really matters
to you or you go you live in the sort of
code world in which you modify you need
to review every change that you make and
and approve it which is a dead end right
because you're like you can only review
codes I remember a couple of years ago
when we first started talking about this
you made the point of 90% of products
are external dependencies. You've got
open source. You've got the requirement
to scale. You've got layers on layers.
And we've had technical debt in the
past. Maybe actually what we're talking
about is with the new Gen AI tools,
we're just going to get an exponential
rise in technical debt. And a video that
you sent me, we're going to play now
because I think it brings to life the
risk in this. This is a I think a really
good kind of summary of the problem.
flight simulator that's going to make me
rich. See, this is all just hype.
Engineers are not going anywhere. You
can't just oneshot the flight
simulator. It's magic. Engineers are
going away soon. Now, make the planes
blue. No, make it realistic like before.
More realistic.
Kind of sums it up. I sent it because it
just brings it along. So, it's it's MLMs
are magic. It is. uses the word on it,
right? They're magic. So, if you
delegate them, but we need to find a way
to to coexist to have a clear line in
which we say these are the decisions
that we want as humans, as the owners of
these systems, as the accountable
entities for these systems of people.
And here are the areas in which we want
to tap into the LLM magic, tap into the
adaptab LLM adaptability, and think
about that kind of played forward,
right? Think about what is software
development in that context. How does
software live over time? what about
dependencies when things come along and
so we think all of that is made possible
in the sort of world of specentric
development and at Tesla what we're
trying to do is we're trying to to say
okay what is this this sort of new
creature this new workflow clearly we're
going to get some of it right we're
going to get some of it wrong we're
going to evolve it I come back to it
being a community play but I think
eventually going down the sort of the
route of just thinking that everything
would be human supervised or thinking
that everything will just be product
supervised you've seen it work they're
dead ends they're going to limit our
ability to use the to tap into these
powers. Makes sense. So two final
questions for you more forwardlooking.
So first is how does the role of the
developer change going forward? Yeah, I
think so. I think software developers
will very much be alive and well. I
think software will be very important
will continue to be critical. The role
the definition of a software developer
will change. I think software developers
will move either up the architect path
in which you need to make more tradeoffs
decisions around like express taste
except preference about do you want to
prioritize for simplicity or do you want
to be extensible those are trade-offs or
do you want and you might get AI support
for it but I think that would be a craft
in which everybody might be able to
build a simple sort of e-commerce site
but if you want to build a novel system
of it you would learn how to do that and
the other path is one of a product side
of having the product sensibility is of
what matters more to users. What I do
think will happen is I think code will
disappear. It would remain just like
assembly remains just like bite code
remains. There would be rare cases in
which you need to deal with it. But most
of the time I think the code should go
away and that's not always a pleasant
statement. I love coding. Coding is fun
on it. And I think part of our task as a
community and as Tesla specifically is
to keep the fun to keep the sense of
creation when you do that versus feel
like you're a supervisor. I think it
makes sense to me. Certainly, I can
imagine specific languages going away.
It's interesting to me that English or
American English is becoming the
language of development in a way that I
just didn't expect would happen anytime
soon. These definitely not British
English. Let's jump into the final
question then. We're seeing companies
not just grow faster than ever because
of PLG. Like Stack One, Bulk. new in our
portfolio has done an amazing job of 0
to 40 million run rate in 14 weeks
something like that's spoken about a
lot. The thing that's most interesting
is just the efficiency of the
organization. It's a small team. It's
approaching $2 million per employee
revenue run rate. So you plot this
forward and very quickly people are
talking about the sort of first billion
dollar oneerson startup. Is that going
to happen? I think so. There's an
interesting question about sort of the
dollars versus the value, right? I
absolutely think that we're not far from
a place in which a single person can
provide value that is equivalent to a
billion dollars of revenue today. I
don't think they will get a billion
dollars for that time. I think if you
harness back like if you hearken back to
the beginning of whatever mid-200s, some
websites had very dynamic real-time
websites and they were very hard to
build and those companies could gain
value or charge more because of that.
Today you can't charge more for that
because that is just the expectation and
I think consumer expectation will grow.
So if a single person can create that
sort of world of functionality and value
then another person next to them and
another person next to them can create
that as well. And so I think supply of
quality software will remain and so I I
guess I I think there will be some
turbulence in value over time. But but I
think that's a bit of a fallacy because
it ignores the fact that the supply I
agree will grow substantially and demand
will remain fixed or maybe grow
somewhat. Maybe there will be a very
tiny window in which we can have these
sort of extremely efficient companies
and I think over time consumers are
going to expect more. I think if you
take the argu I completely agree with
you if you take the argument to the sort
of extreme in order for that to be true
I think these companies would have to go
from zero to a billion dollar run rate
within 24 hours. Yeah. because the speed
that we can all copy anything is like
never before. So, it's a race and
everyone is now going to have to run
faster than they have before. Guy, thank
you so much for the time. I'm going to
hand it across to Luna on the GB team
who's going to introduce our two speed
pitches. Thank you, dude. Thank you.
Well, I hope you enjoyed that session.
Thanks very much, Tom and Gipo. And of
course, if you're in London, do check
out the Google Ventures, the GV London
Genai meetups to see if there's anything
that's on that you could attend in
person as well. Couple of reminders.
Feel free if you enjoyed the session to
subscribe, leave the thumbs up on our
video on YouTube perhaps. And yeah, a
couple of things that are coming up as
well. We have the AI Native DevCon event
which is coming up on May 13th. So
depending on when you're listening to
this recording, do go to a
native.iovents.
io/events. You can register for free and
catch a whole bunch of great content
there. So, what you waiting for? Let's
go ahead and register for free and we'll
see you at the conference. Thanks for
listening and tune in to the next
episode. Bye for
now. Thanks for tuning in. Join us next
time on the AI Native Dev brought to you
by Tesla.
[Music]